Hi, welcome back to Lamrim. Good
morning.
It's early here in Arizona. I guess it's
late wherever you are
or something else.
We're going to start today
with a meditation and
I had to think about what kind of
meditation to do today and
I I thought to teach you guys a special
thing that we do in the monastery, okay?
So
in the Geshe course,
you have to debate
an average 3 hours a day, 4 hours a day,
something and uh
it's out in the hot sun in my time and
it was really hard.
And then sometimes it's under the stars
and it's very beautiful and I I can
remember being in a debate and
Orion rose over my opponent's head and
it was very beautiful.
And uh so
you're not allowed to take any papers to
the debate ground. You you have to
memorize everything before you step into
the debate ground.
And you have to memorize every day
you know, enough material to debate for
2 3 hours.
So
you get very good and they teach you
these methods of short-term memory.
And then you sort of clear it before you
go to bed and then the next day you
start over again.
And uh
there's a process called bhavana, right?
Bhavana. Say bhavana. Bhavana. So
Sanskrit doesn't really have a V, it's
like between a V and a W, ba ba bhavana.
Yeah, and bhava
uh comes from the root bhu
which means to become.
Uh it's different from Buddha a little
bit cuz that's a bu and this is bhu.
So
bhu becomes it it's the source of the
English verb to be.
And so bhava means to be.
And then ana
when you add it to bhava bhava bhavana
it means to make you into something. The
ana is a er in in English or
we have it in English like politician,
musician.
The an it means the person who does
something. So musician is a music player
like Ben Gibson
or politician and then a bhavan
bhavan bhavan is a someone who becomes
something.
Their specialty is to become something.
And that's the Sanskrit word for
meditator.
That's that is the word for meditator.
So it's not
I don't know where meditate comes from,
maybe reach a medium state or something,
but but bhavana meditator
meditation means uh
to become something, to turn yourself
into something.
And there's a special
skill in the monastery. I haven't taught
it for many years. We taught it in New
York many years ago.
Uh we I think we did some kind of
impermanence meditation.
But Lamrim meditation, but
but there's bhavana meditation
means you burn
a pathway into your mind.
So you you take a new series of ideas
like a road map.
Like we had a road map to get with the
GPS to get down here
from Sedona.
And we went a new way and we had a GPS.
It was very beautiful. We went the back
way through Lake Roosevelt and
And
so
on the GPS you get the next piece of the
map, right? Oh, we're going to take you
to Payson to Pine.
Pine and then Payson and then Strawberry
and then
Roosevelt and then Safford. You get each
piece of the road map.
Oh Tim, I'm going to try to talk slower
today.
Okay.
It's just that Geshe makes really good
coffee. Okay.
Uh so
each piece of the road map you get it on
the GPS one by one.
Uh and that's how we're taught to
meditate
in the monastery. So you take pieces
of a larger idea
and then you learn the pieces
and then you then you try to visualize
the whole map in your mind. So you start
with pieces.
Like here's how to get to
Lake Mary
and here's how to go to Payson and
here's how to go to
What's the other one? Pine.
And then here's how to get to
Strawberry. And then slowly you start to
connect them together
until you can visualize the whole route
in your mind.
And
so you learn the pieces
and then you learn to
connect them.
And then you do that trip in your mind
over and over again.
And that's called bhavana because you
make the trip mentally
over and over again and then it burns
itself into your mind and it stays.
And then we can say you learned it. It's
a cool idea. So you take the pieces
you practice the pieces
then you start connecting pieces
together.
And then you practice doing the whole
thing.
And then you keep doing that whole thing
over and over again and it burns itself
into your mind.
And
when it burns itself into your mind and
you can close your eyes and go through
the whole meditation
easily
you become that.
You become that meditation. You see what
I mean? And and then you the the
the the road becomes part of you.
And it's beautiful. It's a beautiful
idea, okay? So
that's the first part of what I want to
start today with you guys for this
retreat. So I'll teach you how to burn
the pieces into your mind.
And then I'll teach you how to do the
whole route. Then I'll teach you how to
repeat the route and then I'll teach you
how to internalize
the route, okay?
And then you become that thing and
that's what Lamrim is all about.
In this case you would
burn
the different methods of reaching
bodhicitta
each each part of the path into your
mind.
Then you would try to repeat the whole
thing.
And then you would do it several times
and then it would become part of you and
you would reach bodhicitta
because you burned it into your into
your mind.
That's the first half, okay?
Then there's a second half
which is mnemonics, okay? M N
e m o n i c s. M N it's a strange word
in English. You don't pronounce the M.
It's m n
e m o n i c s. Yeah, mnemonics.
Uh and those are we use them in the
monastery. Those are memory
assistants, memory triggers, memory
triggers.
Okay? And that's a cool thing
to burn
the route
to bodhicitta into your mind
you make a story. You you make up a
story.
And you base it on something you
experienced already in your life, okay?
Like when I memorized the I memorized
the first three chapters of the
Abhidharmakosha before I knew Tibetan.
Before I learned Tibetan, I could recite
three chapters of the Abhidharmakosha.
In fact, I recited it for Ling Rinpoche
uh one time in the car
and
the senior tutor.
And uh
And the way you do that is you use
pictures uh from your life, something
that happened previously in your life,
okay? And then you
each picture represents a different
idea.
So that's called We're going to use I'm
going to teach you this method
that we use in the monastery to to
bhavana to burn
uh a series of ideas into your mind
so deep that you become that.
And it's very beautiful, okay? And
and it's based on mnemonics. So you you
have to choose a
an event in your life
and that mental latch I'm thinking kind
like having your children or something.
Uh
And you'd probably remember a lot of the
details.
And uh
And then you connect each one to a
concept.
And then you're not going to forget what
happened that day.
You're going to remember the the thing
this happened the water broke then we
ran around and then we decided not to go
to the hospital and
you know, and then each event
each part of a important event in your
life
uh stands for something else in the
meditation. And and that way you don't
miss anything.
And and then slowly that gets burned
into your mind until it becomes you.
And that's the purpose of meditation.
That's what meditation is for. So we're
going to try it for
bodhicitta, okay? So here we go. Don't
don't think it's too complicated. It's
not too complicated.
And it's it's really easy cuz
you have to choose some big event in
your life, okay?
So,
and it's fantastic when you're teaching,
okay? When you're teaching, it's an
important tool.
Uh cuz you actually don't need notes. Uh
you you just
use your mnemonics, you know? So,
I I would like to review the first
class.
And I would like to review the important
ideas of the first class that we had
yesterday.
And I'd like to do that in a meditation.
And I'd like to burn it into my mind.
And so I'm going to use a mnemonic,
okay? So, there were five
main ideas
in the first class yesterday. And when
you teach a class,
you should
try to learn to break it down into the
main ideas
for yourself, just for yourself, so that
you don't have to keep looking at some
paper or something like that.
So, there were five main ideas
in the class in the first class
yesterday,
which which covered the first two of the
10 benefits of bodhicitta. The I hate to
say benefits. 10 cool things
about bodhicitta. And we covered two of
them. We got to two of them in the first
class.
So, I'm using mnemonics, okay? And there
were five
pictures I chose for you guys yesterday
for the first two classes.
And and the pictures were I don't know
if you guys have them available or or
maybe not. You do?
Okay, first picture. It was tennis
player.
Yeah.
And then the So, first picture was a
tennis player.
Second picture was a graduation, right?
Third picture was a dad hugging his
daughter.
Fourth picture was Geshe Michael.
I mean a donkey.
And then uh
the fifth picture was these skyscraper
makers. And that was the whole class.
That was the first class. Those are the
five
important ideas of the first class.
And if I want to meditate on the first
class and burn it into my mind and then
become that, which means to reach
bodhicitta,
uh
then how can I remember those five
pictures? And so for me,
I went to my high school.
Uh
I went to my high school and I walked
around my high school.
And I connected uh
events to I connected parts of the high
school to to the first class that I
taught yesterday, okay?
So, tennis player was easy cuz I was on
the tennis team.
And you know, that was at the tennis
courts.
Then I walked over to the
football stadium, which is where we had
our graduation,
you know? And then I walked down
to where I met my parents at graduation
and they hugged me,
you know? And then I walked by uh
Do you know FFA?
Future Farmers of America, where they
used to keep their animals. That's where
the
donkey was waiting for me.
And then uh
they they uh did some construction on my
high school at at the gymnasium.
And so I I could remember the the
construction, okay? So,
I I'm going to go through that. And so
there you have you have the five main
ideas
of the first class. You have the whole
first class in your mind
uh by connecting it to some
real event in your life, some place you
have been or you remember well, okay?
So, here we go. We're going to turn it
into a meditation. And you got to use
your own
place, okay? Like your high school
probably didn't look like my high
school, so.
All right. It could be the birth of a
child. It could be a house you used to
live in.
Okay?
And it sounds a little complicated, but
it's not. And uh
And then you become an extraordinary
teacher also cuz you don't have to look
at notes.
And you can actually think about what
you're saying. Okay, all right, here we
go.
So, as usual, we'll try to
relax your face, relax your mouth,
relax your eyelids.
Sit up straight.
One way to sit up straight is to push
down,
which forces your
chest and head up.
It's always a good idea to tighten your
lower abdomen in.
The way you do that is uh
on your exhales,
you can use your exhales as a
excuse to tighten your lower abdomen.
And that tightens your
that strengthens your back muscles.
And you can sit up straight, you can
meditate longer.
So, let's take 10 deep breaths and
the exhales
are very very long,
uh
much longer than usual.
So, at the end of the exhale, your tummy
tightens,
which strengthens your back.
And you can sit for
longer periods of time.
Hands are any comfortable way.
The goal with the hands is to keep them
out of the picture, keep them out of the
way.
Just park them.
I don't mind the sun. It's good.
Now, let's go through our five pictures,
okay?
For me, I'm going to use my old high
school.
And I'm going to start on the tennis
courts and
think of a young
young man
who's happy because he just
got a position on the tennis team.
And what that represents is the first
benefit
of bodhicitta, which is you you join the
team
of Mahayana people. Again, it's not a
Mahayana
Buddhist school.
It's a group of
extraordinary beings who have
had the experience of
leaping from planet to planet
and meeting
people
every living being on each planet, tens
of billions of beings
uh on each planet. It's a very very
a special team,
uh
very select group of people called
bodhisattvas.
And if I could
burn this
bodhicitta meditation into my mind,
I could join that team.
How would that feel?
Next,
go to a place
that you remember
that will remind you
of a graduation. Okay?
For me, I I walk from the
tennis courts of my old high school over
to the football stadium.
And that's where we had our graduation.
What's the graduation picture mean?
It means then
the second benefit of Bodhicitta, they
will give you a
title.
You'll have a new title.
They will call you
Bodhisattva Kelsang, Bodhisattva Alex.
Bodhisattva Cutting. And
you'll It's like a PhD title
or doctor title.
Now,
the beings in the universe
who are extraordinary,
they will always talk about you as
as oh, that Bodhisattva
Jigme or that Bodhisattva Tim. Okay?
You will change your identity.
Firstly, I'd like to spend about 10
breaths, 10 slow breaths
on each
part of the path that I'd like to burn
into my mind.
The next idea we learned
was that you get a second title,
which is Kelsang,
daughter or son of the Buddhas.
And for me,
I'm thinking of a picture where my
after my graduation, my my mom and my
dad came and hugged me.
And so, a picture
of a father or mother Buddha
coming to give me a hug
and welcome me into their family. Now,
I'm
their son or their daughter.
And of course, the Buddhas love
everybody, but
once you have jumped between planets and
met all the living beings and made this
commitment to help them directly to
them,
made the commitment directly to them,
each each one individually,
then you sort of join a new family.
And you are welcomed into that new
family.
It's a very
tight-knit family.
And the Buddhas have a special feeling
for you.
Then in my high school picture, I I go
from the football field
where my mom and dad hugged me
after graduation
over to a part of the high school where
there were kids learning to be farmers.
And
they had donkeys.
that donkey reminds me
that we don't have to be
geniuses
or or moral geniuses to become a
Bodhisattva. We don't have to
be the smartest person. We don't have to
be the best person.
We can be
ourselves. We have lots of problems.
We have lots of weaknesses.
We have addictions that we have
not been able to stop.
And we have all kinds of bad habits. We
treat other people
sometimes not very nice.
But still,
we can become a Bodhisattva. It's It's
independent of those things. We can
have that experience. We can have that
dream.
Maybe the worse we are, the better we
can dream.
So,
even in the texts, they even a donkey or
a fish or
a bird,
someone without
great intellectual qualities, someone
who's a normal
person who fails from
day to day, week to week,
even in our practice.
But still, that path is available to us.
We can become a Bodhisattva.
Then the last picture for me at my high
school is I go to the
gymnasium and they built an extra
top on side of on
outside the gymnasium. And I imagine
a skyscraper, people sitting on a piece
of a skyscraper.
And that reminds me of this
event in
in my life where
it seemed like a whole building was
moving,
shaking,
actually jumping from side to side.
And
that reminds me of what happens when any
person
jumps from planet to planet
and reaches
Bodhicitta, becomes a Bodhisattva.
Then because the karma of the whole
universe is linked together,
the karma that created
the physical galaxy,
those karmas are all linked together.
I'm I'm also responsible for Mars. I'm
responsible for the sun.
I'm responsible for Buddha paradises
that I heard about.
And if my
relationship with every living being
changes suddenly,
then that
jolts the karma
that created the galaxy, and the galaxy
jumps
and trembles from the weight
of this new kind of love that I found.
The galaxy is the creation of
my mind, my karma.
And
it serves all living beings. If I decide
to serve those same beings,
then the galaxy has to
jump
when I do. And
people on some level, all all all
people,
and especially all Buddhas, are aware
that one of the one of us in the galaxy
just became a Bodhisattva.
So, imagine the day
that you become a Bodhisattva
and the galaxy
trembles.
And let's dedicate the good karma
that
everyone we know could become a
Bodhisattva.
And then slowly open your eyes.
Take a stretch.
Cool.
Any questions about
anybody here in the room?
Small questions. Poco.
Poco pregunta.
I have Yes. Um
My question is, when the earth shifted
for you, was that your becoming a
Bodhisattva or some other people that
you
experienced becoming a Bodhisattva?
You mean personally?
Yeah. Oh, well.
Can you repeat the question? Yeah, if I
felt the earth shift
under under me, did that mean I became a
Bodhisattva or did it mean that someone
else had become a Bodhisattva?
Uh
Bodhisattvas don't talk about it much.
But uh
if it happens
uh
if it happens to you,
you you'll
you'll know and you'll be very happy.
How's that?
Okay. Any other questions? No.
Let's get to work.
Enough fun.
Uh by the way, uh in a practical
sense,
uh
just a warning, okay?
You can't
you can only do about five scenes
at a time. Like don't try to do 10,
don't try to do 20. You'll go you'll get
weird.
You'll get nervous and
you'll get overloaded and you'll get
grumpy.
Uh do do five pictures well.
Like take choose a high school or some
event in your life and and do the five
well. And the next day do them again and
the next day do them again.
And in the meantime,
this course is going to keep going.
And we're going to cover many other
pictures and you you won't have time to
do all of them. So, don't get uh
frantic.
Don't be one of those frantic
meditators.
You know,
it's like I'm not making enough
progress, you know? Like just calm down
and
do your five pictures, you know?
And uh learn learn them well.
And burn them into the mind. And uh
and skip the ones you didn't have time
to do. And then pick up on the
five pictures like three days later.
That's okay.
And then, you know, you're going to
forget the first five pictures
when you do the second five pictures.
Uh and then you'll feel frustrated. You
feel like, "Oh, I'm not making progress.
I've I already forgot the five pictures
I started with 3 days ago."
And don't think like that, okay? When
you
go through five pictures, you are
burning something into your subconscious
and it will always stay there.
It will always stay there. And it the
second time you do it, it'll come up
very fast.
And the third, you know, like years
later you'll be teaching Lamrim
at Diamond Mountain and something you
burned in there 40 years ago will
come up and that means it's part of you,
okay? Everything you think of
is becomes part of you, whether you're
conscious of it or not.
So, nothing is wasted. No energy is
wasted. Newton was correct. Okay. All
right. Here we go.
We're going back to our class.
Uh
I'm at Dana. I don't know what
d e s n a.
Cha c h o s, right? That's where I
That's where I am in the text.
Okay. I guess Tim got there.
Don't worry about it. Dana Chip
Chip Gete Shitongyi Nyingpo Nying Zinna
D Nyi Ngay Met.
Uh
Nying Zin is an interesting word. Say
Nying Zin.
Nying means the face of something. Zin
means to hold it.
And Nying Zin means to identify somebody
or recognize somebody. And he says, "If
you want to Nying Zin Nyingpo." What's
Nyingpo?
The heart. If you would like to identify
the heart of the Gete Shitong. Gete
Shitong means 84,000, okay?
And this is a tradition from the
Abhidharma that says that Lord Buddha
taught 84,000 tumbos, skandas,
mountains
of Dharma, okay? Like how many teachings
did Lord Buddha give? We have 990
books
in John Brady's database spoken by Lord
Buddha.
Uh but that's a
that's about 1/84 of what he taught on
this earth.
So, he taught 84,000
different mountains of teachings.
Uh
why 84,000? For $100. Um there's 84,000
mental mental factors.
Yay! $100 to Janice.
Yeah, there's 84,000 different negative
parts of your mind. So, Buddha had to
teach 84,000 different
heap and there's a big debate about
what's a heap of scripture.
One opinion
is that it's the amount that a magical
elephant could carry
called Rupton and that's a big story,
but long story.
But uh
anyway, he says, "If you wanted to
identify Nying Zin
the essence of the 84,000
mountains of teachings, millions of
pages of teachings,
D Nyi Ngay Met. D Nyi Ngay Met.
It's nothing other than what I just
taught you.
It's the five scenes at your high
school.
Okay? You want the essence
of every sutra and tantra ever taught?
It's Bodhicitta.
Okay? It's to be a Bodhisattva.
Is Is if you had to choose one
teaching from the 84,000
huge groups of teachings
that was the heart of the Buddha's
teachings, D Nyi Ngay Met, you wouldn't
find anything better
than those five pictures, okay?
All right. Um
Jowo Je Pal Chiky Kyang
Sem Drel Tong Channyin Je Chanchub Sem
Kong Chawa Konchog Sum Kyi
Somebody asked uh Lord Atisha, which
here is called Jowo Je, which means the
Lord, right? Uh
and they also call him Pal Chiky. Who
can guess Pal Chiky?
Yeah, the one angel. Nice.
20 bucks.
Cat.
Okay, Jime, don't forget. Uh
I was going to say 20 bucks. I just
didn't have time.
Uh
Yeah, Pal Chiky means the the one
divine being. So, sometimes Atisha is
called Pal Chiky.
He's called the one angel, okay? It's a
beautiful name.
Pal Chiky Kyang he said,
"Look, Sem Drel Le Tong.
Give up on this life. Focus on Champa
and Nying Je and Chanchub Sem, which
we're going to talk about in the next
retreat.
You know, focus on the steps to get into
Bodhicitta, which is love,
compassion, and then Bodhicitta, okay?
Konchog.
Just focus on that. Don't get distracted
by anything else. Just do that, okay?
Um
I think it's important to say what does
it mean
when Atisha says, "Give up on this
life."
And I remember uh you know, I I've I've
seen so many strange things in Dharma
teaching.
You know, I've got like 50 years of
Dharma teachings
that I that I've been to.
And
I remember
we were in New Jersey
and we were kind of out in the
countryside.
And there was a
like a few acres of
of woodlands, swampy woodlands across
the street.
Okay? And this is called Pyramid Acres
in New Jersey.
The rest is all gasoline refineries, but
there was this one little probably
polluted
swamp.
And uh
one of the students in the class that
Khen Rinpoche said, "Sandy le tong, give
up on this life." And he packed up his
house and he moved across the street
into the forest.
And uh
he lasted about 2 days.
And Rinpoche was so funny. He just said,
"Leave him, you know, he'll come he'll
be back in
in a day or two." And the guy struggled
back after 2 days. He said, "I need a
house, I need a bed, I need a
refrigerator, you know." So,
it doesn't mean uh
quit your job or divorce your wife or
tell your kids to go away. It doesn't
mean that. It
give up on this life
means look your projects, all the
projects you do.
Right? Alex has a new project.
You know, and look,
guess what?
Sometimes it's going to go good and
sometimes it's going to go messy.
And sometimes it's going to be smooth
club club de oro. It's sometimes it's
going to be very fun. And then sometimes
it's going to be a total headache.
And nothing goes right. And
de le tong,
give it up, you know, just relax, okay?
Look,
that's the way it goes. That's the way
samsara is.
You know, you try to raise money for
stupa, you have a message with teaching,
then suddenly everyone's
confused, upset, and you're like, "Okay,
just relax, okay? Everybody just relax,
okay?"
Things mess up in samsara, okay? That's
the way it is.
Just relax, have fun.
Le tong, you know, give it up.
You know, focus on
whatever happens in your project.
The the good things go well, things
don't go well.
The only thing that matters is do you
love the other people in the project?
That's all that matters, okay?
Maybe the money will come, maybe the
money won't come.
Maybe we'll succeed to buy the storage
for some maybe we won't succeed.
But the main thing is the only important
thing is love the other people in the
project.
And then then it's successful, okay? Cuz
it's never going to be
smooth, it's never going to work all the
time.
Just get used to it. That That's what it
means to give it up.
Give up this idea that success is
the project makes money and there's a
big stupa and
give up this idea.
Success means the people in the project
are
feeling deep love for each other. That's
success, okay? That's what Atisha said.
All right. Kona, that's all.
All right.
We have reached the fourth benefit. Who
can tell me the first three?
Uh
I I can tell you number two. Come on.
Where did the high school start?
You had a tennis player. Yeah, you
joined the team.
I joined the team.
Second. You get a name. Or you call you
call the Bodhi. Yeah, you got a name and
that one importantly includes a hug from
your parent. And then what was the third
one? Oh, this is the encouragement stage
where any idiot can become one.
No, it's something else.
No, we only covered the first two
benefits in the five pictures. There was
another benefit
yesterday. Well, what was the review
from last
time last summer? Yeah.
Yeah, but what was the third benefit?
Third benefit is that list number of
diamonds. Good. Yeah, outshining. Silky
number, okay?
Uh I'm sorry. Uh a Bodhisattva outshines
millions of nice people.
Okay? Nice people are nice, but a
Bodhisattva, I'm sorry, it's just
different it's a different level.
They're jumping from planet to planet
directly helping billions of people.
It's It's nice to fundraise for stupa.
It's nice, it's a good thing.
But it's But a Bodhisattva is a
different It's a totally different
level. It's billions of times bigger.
You know, and
and it's more efficient. If you could
reach that,
you could help billions of people and
not just a few, okay? So, that should be
a goal, right? And you can do it.
All right.
So, now's the fourth benefit. We have a
picture from Paul Pachi, I don't
remember who this is.
Yeah, and uh I like this picture because
I'm trying to open a coffee shop.
It's
I'm loving all the county inspectors.
Uh
nothing is going right.
And
what's this picture represent? So, burn
it into your mind, okay?
This is the fourth benefit.
And it's that if you do become a
Bodhisattva, this is so cool.
I I have to say it
correctly.
If you do get to be a Bodhisattva,
tiny little things
that other people do for you
who don't even know you're a
Bodhisattva,
become extremely heavy karma for them.
Okay? So, you're just a powerful karmic
object and nobody knows.
Okay? Somebody makes you a coffee,
uh it's going to take them to Buddha
paradise for 100 lifetimes.
And
you can't go telling people that, you
know, they're going to think you're an
egomaniac, right?
"Oh, thanks for giving me $100. Now
you're going to go to Buddha paradise
for 1,000 lifetimes."
I mean, you can't say that to people.
They'll think you're just trying to
collect $100 and stuff. So,
but the fact is if you become a
Bodhisattva,
then tiny little things that people do
for you, you can have the pleasure
of knowing
that little things that people do for
you
are going to cause them intense
lifetimes of
happiness
just because of who you are.
It's It's very sexy, right?
Because of who you are,
uh and you don't have You can't tell
people, right? They'll just say, "Oh,
you're just trying to get more coffee."
You know,
uh
but you can enjoy
deeply
uh the pleasure
that because you're a Bodhisattva,
when somebody else
helps you or even somebody, I don't
know, puts the gas in your car or
something,
that
they're going to go to some paradise for
lifetimes cuz they did something for
you.
Because you are You've You have had the
experience of helping billions of
people.
So, you're a heavy karmic You're much
heavier karmic object than their parents
or anything like that, right?
And that's just fun. It's just fun to be
a person like that.
You know, then you kind of find excuses
to
to have nice interactions with people
because it helps them.
You see what I mean?
Uh so, somebody tries to cheat you or
or
screw you or something, and then you
just find a way to turn it into a nice
in interaction.
Uh
and then it helps them. And it's really
fun. Somebody tries to
cut in the line in front of you.
And you say, "Yeah, go ahead, you know.
It's nice to see you."
And uh
that that gives them intense good karma.
So, it's nice to be that kind of a
special
karmic object anonymously, right? You
don't tell them You can't tell people.
But you can quietly rejoice all day
just for I don't know, politicians who
who create your internet or your roads
or
strange people, you can rejoice
in strange
What do you call it?
Politicians who want to be famous, who
only want to be famous,
but they're still helping you.
And then you can You can enjoy that
they're helping you cuz they're making
such good karma. You see what I mean?
Like that.
All right.
Here's the text. Shipani.
Chanchu gi sum gyu la kyena, if you're
able to get
the Bodhisattva's
state of mind,
bodhicitta. Jig ten la me che pe chak
chak gyur.
You become someone who is worthy of the
of the People should throw themselves on
the floor around you.
It would be appropriate.
But
But that's the fourth benefit, okay? You
become this kind of person.
Uh,
Shamir means
even the devas, even the superheroes
from
Marvel Comics
should be throwing themselves on the
floor, okay?
Chakchar cure What Okay, $50.
Worthy of prostration. Sounds good.
Word worthy.
Come on.
Argh.
Argh. Arghat.
Arghat. Okay. Yeah, all right.
There's another Okay, for another $50,
there's another way to read arghat.
Arihat. Arihan.
Yeah, enemy destroyed. Yay. Okay, $50.
Jingme paid Jingme $50.
Bow down to yourself while you're at it.
Okay, char ladon che pe che pe shing
chok tu gyur. You become shing chok.
Shing chok means uh,
highest
person in the room that people could
make offerings to, okay? And again, of
course, you don't announce that. You
don't run around and say, "Hey, anyone
who gives me a pizza is going to
Medicine Buddha's paradise, you know?"
It doesn't make you popular, okay?
Uh,
Okay.
Next picture, you guys.
By the way, now you see why I like to
use pictures cuz I use them for my
meditation and I I use them as
meditation triggers, okay?
Memory triggers, okay? This is a lady,
uh, professional
diver,
uh, professional Olympic level
high diver.
And there's a cute story where I met
this lady.
Uh, so I
I when I went to Princeton, I didn't
know anybody
outside of Arizona, nobody.
And I got off the plane and uh,
I went
I went and asked someone, "How do I get
to Princeton from John F. Kennedy
Airport?" They said, "You have to take a
private plane."
They cheated me. You actually take a
bus.
And uh, so
I took a private plane. It cost me like,
you know, nowadays it'd be like $2,000.
And uh,
you know,
went there and I was so naive, you know?
I lost half my money the first day.
And then uh,
you know, I showed up in a suit,
in a green suit
that my mother said everybody at
Princeton would wear.
And everyone was dressed in tie-dye and
they had long hair and it was the hippie
times. And I like took the suit off in
like 5 minutes,
you know? And then I
I remember I went to sign up for my
room, you know?
And I got an assignment to a room. They
said, "You're staying with three other
people, you know, in a suite."
And I said, "Okay, you know?" And I went
there
and I knock on the door and these three
beautiful girls come out.
And I'm like,
"Is this my room?" And I said They said,
"No, no, you can't stay here." And I'm
like, "No, look, it's my room."
They were the Olympic divers
going to Princeton, you know? I got a
scholarship to Princeton. Anyway,
unfortunately, the school figured it out
that it was a mistake.
And but I never forgot the professional
diver thing. Why is Why are we showing
this picture, Geshe la? Come on, get to
the point.
Uh, Kadam Kunga Gyaltsen Gong Gyur la
Sug Dran.
He starts to talk about
how much hard work
and discipline
it takes
to have the Bodhisattva's experience. He
starts to talk about
how much hard work
and discipline
it takes
to have the experience of jumping from
planet to planet, okay? And
and I think it's important that we get
this lecture
from Pabongka Rinpoche. You know, look,
it's fun to jump from planet to planet.
It's fun to be the kind of person when
someone offers you a coffee, they're
going to go to Buddha paradise for like
10 lifetimes.
That's all beautiful stuff, but look,
and it's like the warning on the
cigarette package, you know? It's hard
work. It does You don't get there
easily. It takes years of hard work, you
know? People ask me, "Uh, Geshe la, I
just want to do mantras.
Uh, I don't want this hard work. I don't
want to study for year after year, you
know?"
Uh, here's Pabongka's answer,
the greatest lama of the past century, I
would say.
Uh, Kadam Kunga Gyaltsen.
The first Buddhist in Tibet, the Kadampa
Ka Ka Kadampas, they used to say,
"The reason people are
practicing tantra, diamond way, with a
special Buddha deity
and uh, Jang Gyun Ngak, a special
mantra, the reason they the reason we
gave those people
a a tantric Buddha to meditate on and a
mantra to do is because they were not
capable of learning the Dharma."
Okay?
It I didn't
Sum Gyur Chos Shing Med Pel Len.
The problem was
they couldn't meditate. So, we gave them
that. You see what I mean? Now, of
course, it's an exaggeration.
Okay? Of course, it's an exaggeration.
That's what teachers do. They try to
shock you.
Sum Med Dran Med Tim Med Rom Med Rig
Char Med. There's nothing to see,
nothing to hear, nothing to smell,
nothing to taste. Of course, there's
something to see, there's french fries.
Uh, you know? But they try to shock you.
So, the early Buddhists uh, used to say,
"Why is this guy spending all his time
on
some
secret
tantric Buddha or and with some
mantras?"
And they said, "Well, it's easy
to explain. He didn't have anything to
meditate on."
So, they gave him that. You see? So, he
didn't have a practice.
Uh,
so they're criticizing that
the lazy It can be laziness, right? Uh,
they're saying, "Look, if you want to be
a Bodhisattva, which you should be,
it's hard work and it takes a lot of
hard work. It's like being an Olympic
level athlete. You know, it takes hours
of hard work every day.
It doesn't come easy, you know? If it
came easy,
then everybody would be jumping from
planet to planet. It's fun,
you know? And it takes discipline. It It
takes
practice. You got to practice. You got
to work hard, okay? Den Nga Sum Den Nga
Ba Ta Jo Tub Sum Chung Yang Ne Che Te.
Uh, and he says uh,
"Every chance you get
to hear a little bit more from about the
Bodhisattva, every chance you get
to hear a little bit more about what is
a Bodhisattva, you should grab it.
You know, if if you have a choice
between
uh, running to the bathroom during this
class
or waiting until the class is over, wait
until the class is over, even if you're
uncomfortable,
cuz during that pee-pee time, you might
miss some seeds,
some bakchaks, okay? Like, try to get
every little
sentence you can about how to be a
Bodhisattva because
because it's not it's never wasted,
right? Chumisawa.
One of the four laws of karma
is that everything you ever experience
has an indelible effect on you
at some point. So, try to
expose your mind
to high words, high ideas
every chance you get
because they will have an inevitable
effect on you
to become a Bodhisattva. So, keep
keep trying to learn more and and be
disciplined, okay?
Tub Sum Chung Yang Ne Che Te. Extremely
important. And Tim, I know I have one
more minute. I'm I'm I'm on it, okay?
Nga Sangye Kyab Sum Kyi Da. Tub Sum Gyin
Ngon Mang Ngak Kyab Sang Kyi Ne Dem Ba.
Tong.
Every little thing you expose your mind
to
in the Dharma,
every sentence from the Lam Rim,
every time you do another mantra,
you are planting.
Somebody asked me a a I don't know, it's
a silly question. If I say mantras, am I
planting seeds?
If you go to the bathroom, you're
planting seeds, okay?
Okay. Mantras is a little bit better. Of
course, you're planting seeds. Very
powerful seeds. Extremely powerful
seeds, okay? Nga Sangye Kyab Sum Kyi Da.
And he gives an example.
There was a flock of
ducks
flying over the Buddha when he was
giving a teaching one time and they
heard his voice,
okay? And because of that, it planted a
seed in their hearts.
They were born as
devas,
you know, in the in a temporary
paradise,
and they all saw emptiness after that.
Okay?
Because they didn't go to the bathroom
during the class.
Okay?
They
They heard that one more sentence from
the Buddha.
Uh
they heard him speak. They just heard
his
They were attracted to the sound of his
voice. They didn't know what he was
saying.
But they thought it was beautiful. It
sounded like another
goose or something making nice quacking
noises.
And because of that, they put seeds in
their minds. So, he says, "You know,
work hard.
Every single opportunity you get
to hear something more,
take it.
Without getting nervous and what do you
call that?
Stressed Dharma people are the most un-
pleasant thing, you know?
Don't be a stressed Dharma person, okay?
Relax.
You know, sitting in the class, I had a
person who loved to lay down in the
class.
I If you be in the class, it's better
you lay down than you not be in the
class, okay?
And you'll hear something, and that will
put seeds in your mind,
and they will inevitably affect you
later, okay? So,
work You have to work hard, you know?
Don't think lamrim is a waste of time or
studying the Guiding Light gives me a
headache. Of course it gives you a
headache.
But uh
I'll tell you something from 68 years
old, okay?
Uh there's nothing valuable in this
world
which doesn't come with hard work, okay?
To get something valuable,
to get something precious, it takes hard
work. It takes discipline, okay?
All right. See you in the next class,
guys.
Take a break.